hello welcome thanks everyone it's
February 1st 2023.
we're in meeting 14.
cohort 2 of the paradol textbook
were on chapter six
so
today we can
look over
any and all of the questions on chapter
six
that have been raised
we can also go to the text but just to
begin does anyone want to bring up any
quote or
topic or or anything about chapter six
or any section from the text or question
that someone wants to go to first or a
general point about chapter six
um Ali and then anyone else
uh well I think now that the white paper
from versus lab is published it might be
a good idea to read designing ecosystems
white paper along with chapter six
because it can provide a much wider
perspective and see how
uh how the research in developing these
kinds of active inference based AI uh is
currently developing and uh to see how
the plan for the future developments
have already been
discussed especially in the the case for
uh sympathetic and shared intelligence
which uh is kind of
long-term plan to develop those kinds of
intelligence systems so yeah I think
this paper can
immensely help to see the big picture
related for Designing these kinds of
um
active imprint space models
awesome
thanks yeah the the first 20 pages of
the paper have great points but just to
jump to the the timeline part
it's 2023. this was released at the end
of 22.
and
in the coming years
here are some doubling timelines that we
might expect or prefer
so that does help set the stage
um for chapter
six
um
anyone else you just unmute or just
raise your hand
chapter six is a recipe for building
active inference models so it's not the
uh
fast food restaurant yet but it's a
recipe
for the home and potentially industrial
chef
it covers the essential steps to design
an effective model
and that is going to be taken in like a
staged way
um
and
starts on page
105 in the textbook so
shall we look at the questions does
anyone have a specific question they
would like to jump to or any general
points
otherwise let's look at the recipe
and then
see if there's things that we can add
and then in this active inference model
recipe
um
let's
see if we can flesh it out with what
we're seeing and learning
from doing modeling
and also how it's similar and difference
from
other modeling recipes
how different is this than doing a
linear regression model how different is
it than doing some other type of
modeling or analysis
give me six chapters to model active
inference and I'll spend the first four
on the generative model
Carl Lincoln
which system are we modeling
what is the appropriate form for the
generative model
how to set up a generative model how to
set up a generative process so those
have been copied out here
does anyone just want to give some
comments on these stages or how it one
just Briefly summarize
what each of these four stages are and
what they do
or just any feature about these four
steps
I guess one thing is they need to be
discrete
these steps
um and that's
already a decision that needs to be made
do you mean the steps are separate from
each other
yeah
and we need to have categories let's um
if we if we have these um hidden states
in the Markov model
um these are
separate states
and um
I guess that's a
it's a kind of a problem and a
restriction also
are there other modeling approaches that
you think
don't have such restriction
yeah for instance in neural networks
um
these Transformer models where you can
type in whole
uh a whole picture for instance
or something like this
I may be wrong so maybe maybe there's
categories to
yes well maybe a related question is
when we specify what is a hidden State
and what is an observation in our
generative model
are we kind of locked into that
or
is it possible for
something like a pre pomdp
that describes
the structure
potentially this is between steps two
and three
like the hidden state is going to be an
image
and then it gets set up with a certain
dimensionality
foreign
can raise their hand let's just
look through the questions see which
what we can bring into the modeling page
and um
like which ones are remaining to be
needed why is modeling of the generative
process a necessary step for building an
active inference model
okay we have a lot of notes on here what
would somebody just give on a first pass
why is the generative process a
necessary step for building active
inference model
I guess on a very high level
um because the generative model is
ultimately creating a representation of
the generative process
if we want to create that model we have
to
allow for the generative model to be
able
to model the generative process so we
also need to model the generative
process
yeah
one aspect there is the generative model
is or the general process is providing
the observations
and then the sort of
the second layer on that is the
generative model
is working with or is building
representations or is a good regulator
of or is needing to maintain the
requisite diversity to deal with the
generative process
so it would be like asking why is
modeling of the grid important in a net
logo agent-based simulation
it's like well you got two kinds of
things
the agents moving around the grid and
you have the grid
so in this
active inference particular partition
we have the generative model that's the
active entity
and then we have the generative process
which could be another active entity
or it can have any structure
so like in model stream 7.2
the generative model was an active agent
the generative process was just an if
then logic
Ali
I also think that these
uh distinctive steps that have been
outlined here in this chapter as a
recipe to designing
um any active inference model are not
necessarily uh are not specifically
distinct or even sequential steps
because uh for example in the first step
it says which system are we modeling
but on the other hand the choice of
sorry
the choice of the system that we're
modeling would inevitably uh would it
have an effect on how on the type of the
generative model or the the type of the
general the process we're dealing with
so in a sense all of these steps are
kind of intertwined into each other and
they're not
necessarily uh have to be seen as a kind
of a sequence in a sequential order but
rather in a kind of uh from a
hierarchical point of view we just need
to have which component of the modeling
process are we dealing with so for
example we can possibly Begin by
identifying the generative process and
then
uh look at how we can optimally
represent the generative process uh by a
suitable generative model so what I'm
saying is these four steps are not
necessarily something that uh to be
taken on the pace level they are just
laying out the the Territorial map of
modeling those systems and we might
begin from uh each of one and each one
of them and then
proceed to any other depending on the
situation we're involved then
yeah thank you it it may be
seen as an atemporal
partition
not necessarily the order that a
traditional recipe would have
let's let's continue on and so we can
just touch on on each of the questions
okay what are the four steps some of
this material we moved over to this
distinct model recipe page just so that
we can develop that
um in its own section
um
okay
what are the four steps that are being
addressed on that page
in figure 6.1 what did the
unidirectional and bi-directional arrows
mean
what's a thought anyone has on this
so
in a Bayesian graph the nodes represent
random variables and the edges
represents statistical influences
those can be represented in an
undirected fashion if there's no
arrowheads and that's a lot like a
structural equation model
like if we were dealing with linear
Notions of correlation Pearson
correlation we could make a structural
equation model
and then the edges would be like
correlations between two variables which
are undirected of course
in a Bayesian causality
framework like Judea Pearl
at all
it is possible to have a bi-directional
arrow
um which is a lot like an undirected
but also you can have a unidirectional
Arrow such that like changes in one
variable
cause changes in another but not
asymmetrically especially if you
consider time series information
um
in the work of Aguilera at all how
particular is the free energy how
particular work I think
um
there are several papers and and a
stream on it
they analyze
which topologies of the action
perception Loop have which properties
so one can imagine like a simple
cybernetic action perception Loop like
which we could just call like around the
clock so no line in the middle just
internal states only influence action no
no backwards arrow action only
influences internal internal onsense
Sense on internal and all the self loops
um that's like a simple Around the Clock
topology of the action perception Loop
so then we can ask all right so from
that around the clock
uh
causal framing
what extra edges and arrowheads exist in
the way that it's shown in figure 6.1
there are three
there's the connection between active
and sensory States so the blanket states
have an additional relationship
and
there's this somewhat interesting
symmetry
where active states have an arrow back
to internal States
and sensory states have an arrow back to
external States
frankly I am not sure to what extent
people are just showing representations
of the way that previous models have
shown it
which could be in a graphical
representation like this or you could
think of this as the adjacency Matrix of
the causal influence of the four states
on each other
like those that could be a fully
connected Matrix with a value in every
cell or it could be like just the
identity Matrix would be like four
states that are independently evolving
and not influencing each other
um
different topologies
of this particular partition are going
to have different properties
and I think the most General approach
would be to do structure learning and
Bayesian model selection on different
topologies for the action perception
Loop
so what do they mean
well they mean that you are
um
comparing models
with the constraints or the availability
for that parameter value to be non-zero
if you delete the arrowhead of a certain
kind
then you're basically testing models
within a restricted class where that
parameter has been fixed at zero
so if you want to fix the effect of
sensory States on external states to
zero
maybe you think that's quote unrealistic
so you want to fix that to zero
so that you have increased statistical
power to resolve other parameters
that's valid although one of the most
intuitive
um reasons to do so which is like but
sensory states don't influence external
states in the real world it's like yes
but that's the map territory fallacy
this isn't the causal structure of
reality
Ali or anyone else
uh actually it might be helpful to look
at figure two from the paper pass
integrals particular kinds and strange
things and especially the different
typologies of the particular kinds
provided there being inert particles
active particles conservative
conservative and strange particles so
briefly they Define inert particles as
the kind of particles or systems with no
active States
and in the in the order of increasing
complexity uh one uh one step further or
one uh one level
up would be the active particles which
is a particle with a non-empty set of
active States but then uh ultimately we
and also the conservative particle is a
is an active particle whose particle
whose particular States follow Paths of
least action but ultimately
we reach a kind of definition uh I
believe for the first time for strange
particles which are defined as
conservative particles whose activist
states do not directly influence
internal States
so uh this paper claims that only this
fourth type of particles namely the
strange particles
have the capacity uh to be a kind of
sentient agent or any kind of uh
intelligent agent depending on how we
Define intelligence or sentience
but in any case all of these kind of
this strange particles some some uh
subsumes all the other kinds of
particles
but with varying uh levels of complexity
uh assigned to each of them
thank you
yes
good connection here we see
um so interestingly
we don't see
the backwards Arrow
here we see the Around the Clock
and the intra blanket connections
but we're we don't have the backwards
Edge
yeah that's because uh these kinds of
strange particles uh have not been
developed into a fully sentient agents
yet so to be fully sentient is to be
able to actively uh influence all the uh
the uh the active and sensory States so
I believe that's why we don't have those
bi-directionality in this uh picture for
strange particles yet
thank you
yes it's almost like this is one circuit
diagram
it's like we have four
CPUs on our circuit board that's the
particular partition
and then how we wire
up the topology of the particular
partition
is like the hardware of our circuit
board and then what
the Dynamics are is like the software of
our circuit board
foreign
once we start mixing in these um
taxonomies of particles of increasing
sentience and cognitive complexity
and then we start mixing in the blanket
index like it's a big space
but also it's a very semantic space
and
one advantage of fep and active modeling
is we can develop special or reduced
cases of particular things
that are
sub cognitive but they're still broadly
considered within a cognitivist
framework
whereas something like thousand brains
it may be a super effective architecture
for inference
or generalization or any other number of
advanced cognitive tasks
however
it cannot be
constrained or projected down
to the case of like a ball rolling down
a slope
whereas Bayesian mechanics Bayesian
physics
and this
um taxonomy of particles
helps us Bridge the continuum
with expressive modeling framework
that spans
the simplest
least active particles to open-ended
complexity and intelligence
Michael
yeah I I also had a little bit of
problems with understanding this inter
um blanket uh Markov blanket Loop and
what that could mean
um
so there's somehow unmediated
action that does not have an impact on
the environment
and The Sensation
sensation action loop I I have problems
really to understand what that is what
that could be
and
um
I mean I can see that one can have a
system that produces something like this
but I have understanding uh problems to
understand so I was thinking whether
This was meant to be for instance a
reflex you hit on the knee and then
the leg
does some kind of movement
but without going to the brain so that
um
the nerve ends in the spine somewhere
and then this action is produced by uh
by placing the spine and and then it
doesn't go too
but it's I mean that it depends on what
you call an internal state right so if
the spine that triggers this reaction
uh not part of an internal State I I
well I'm I'm a little bit lost in
understanding what how we how we can
understand that yeah thank you for the
comments so
super important Point like it depends
what is internal States it's not like
States
um
even within a fixed like we're these are
the only variables on the table
um
whether one is internal or external
is of course whether we're choosing to
model it as the generative model or a
generative process like which side of
the blanket and there's a symmetry there
um and then it's not just like this
variable is an internal State it's
always like the four-fold particular
partition comes into being
in
the same time
like the blanket states are those that
make internal and external States
conditionally independent
so but that blanket state with respect
to X and mu
it might be an internal state with
respect to something else
so it does definitely depend on it and I
think now to the question of the
connection
here's from emperor's new Markov
blankets by vernberg
um
I think the edge may have to do with
just the
uh the fact that there is an arrowhead
doesn't mean that the parameter value is
non-zero
it just means that we're describing
families of models where there can be a
non-zero influence we're not a priori
fixing it to zero but you could
conceivably remove this Edge and just
fit the simple around the clock or
around the clock with the two backwards
edges
so because we're making models not
um of maps not territories
we don't need to be constrained to a
physical
um anatomical realism with respect to
what these edges are
and so it's easy to sort of contrast the
plausibility of these edges with
anatomical realism
but these are not anatomical edges
so it's just opening up this the family
of models under consideration
to a non-zero statistical influence
between these states
and it also May inherit from
um the
um the question of co-parents
and also the developments of what people
call a friston blanket
whereas the Markov blanket formalism by
Pearl
was initially characterized on an
undirected graph and there was only one
kind of blanket state
it was just the set of nodes that make
internal and external States
conditionally independents
and um you could imagine a sort of clean
friston blanket with like a clean
division of labor where
there's um some of the nodes in the of
that blanket set
are strictly outgoing
and some of the nodes are strictly
incoming
so that could happen you could buy
dictate Design Systems that have that
characteristic and that may map onto
a anatomical realism
but also you might want to consider
parameterizations of models that don't
have such a clean
partitioning
like there's a dual functional node
that has an incoming and an outgoing
statistical dependency
and that doesn't have to map on to any
actual sensor or actuator in the world
it's just a statistical note
um
but isn't okay I can see that one can
design such a system but does it make
sense
I mean if there's an infinite Loop
between active States and sensory states
that mutually manipulate themselves but
they have neither
an impact on an external world not on an
internal
how
of course we can assume this but what is
the re what is the reasoning there
I mean does it make sense if if
something happens and we cannot see it
and and not outside not inside but it's
the point
it's like just like a full turing
machine that generates a derivation tree
with huge number of internal load that
just disappear and one has not a track
of what happens there
yes thank you for the comment so I think
one one way to
think about
um
this
topology this wiring of the particular
partition here's from that um
uh path integrals particular kind
strange things paper
this is how we're modeling flows over
states in the fep
we have the flow over the total
particular partition X
is like a tuple there's a four unit four
four length Vector over internal
external sense and action States
and
the flows of each of these nodes
are a function of
if it were all by all connected so if
there was like an edge here
then you could just like the fully
connected model would be
um
each of the flows would be a function of
all four other variables
and and you can
um
you could write that out if you wanted
but importantly
in these bottom two the action and the
internal or the autonomous States
don't have a direct Reliance on external
States
the uh Etta is not in the bottom two
and then importantly the external and
the sense States
don't have a direct
they're not taking as an argument
internal States directly
that
is like the minimal
cybernetic constraints
we might be then interested in
constraining further
but and it
fep maybe General May apply to the to
the um all by all case as well
but this is the minimal constraint
that allows autonomous States
octave and internal
to be under
um perceptual and action selection
imperatives
we don't want to have our finger on the
scale
on external States or sensory States
directly
except through action
so in any given case
the topology
itself could be a structure learning
question or given a fixed apology
parameterizing it is is going to be the
question
but does it make sense it's like saying
does a given structural equation model
make sense
it just is a function of what data you
have
let's see if we can just touch upon
subsequent questions
is there a common good representation of
rubric for evaluating GM GP
does anyone have any thoughts
well
one approach that's not even active
specific is using the Bayesian
information Criterion
or its cousin the AIC the ikiki
and um the Bic and and basically the AIC
reward good fit and they penalize models
with more parameters so the bic is
widely used to
establish
the Pareto optimal trade-off
of model complexity and model accuracy
so if one is interested in like what is
a good generative model generative
process fit
if you just want the sheer
um Fitness
you're going to end up on the slippery
slope towards High dimensional
generative models because adding a new
parameters
appropriately strictly increases model
likelihood
because new parameters are always
sucking up variants that was left
unexplained in the noise term by
whatever you had previously
so we don't just want to Simply increase
the likelihood blind to all other
factors we want some sort of balanced
measure that penalizes adding more
parameters so that's one approach for
model evaluation in the Bayesian space
and another that is commonly used is a
Bayes Factor which is a relative measure
of
fit
amongst multiple Bayesian models
so the base factor is a ratio between
two Bayesian models
and so it can be used
um people have kind of heuristics just
like there are heuristics for p-values
not even going into the whole question
about p-values here
but there are also heuristics for Bayes
factors
whether the evidence of one model over
another is like substantial strong
decisive Etc
and
base Factor allow any models to be
compared with each other
whereas if we were in the parametric
modeling space
we would only be able to test using the
hierarchical ratio likelihood ratio test
the hlrt for parametric models
so for parametric models you can only
test nested models like if you're doing
an anova you can test an effective a an
effective B and then you can compare
that with whether there's an interaction
between a and b
but you would have a hard time testing a
model with a and b
versus a model with b and c unless you
put that into a nested parametric
framework
Bayesian statistics gives us a lot more
flexibility to compare models
so model selection evaluation comparison
those are
big areas
short answer we're using Bayesian
statistics so we have the most modern
tools for evaluating that
in a specifics it's always going to be
the specifics
but in terms of the tools for model
selection Bayesian statistics has the
best tools
all right how does the particular
partition
so 6.1 which we were looking at earlier
or the sort of Proto
particular partition
the the
um the dyadic partition here informal
relate to the pumdp in figure four three
what would anyone say
these are two common
figures that we see
but I don't see X mu U and Y
here
though interestingly
the X and the y in the continuous time
representation
they actually do map on
to the particular partition
and
um kind of with a v
whereas the discrete time pomdp
does not use this exact notation
what would anyone say why do we have
this closed
cybernetic
partition
but then it looks like we're moving into
a pomdp model with a different topology
I guess in the p-o-mdp model there
should be also
an arrow going backwards to the
beginning of the so if we and in a in a
state on the right side there should be
somehow a loop back to the beginning
which is your implicit somehow
that is called sophisticated active
inference
where in the past present and future
there can be an inference over the past
present and future
okay yeah so it is it is possible but
it's not the base case
yeah no yes
so this is uh unrolled in the time now
actually yes exactly exactly this has no
time
the particular partitions
are not defined in time
they're defined as functions of other
states in the partition
because what a Bayes causal graph
represents
is not
as a function of type
so it has to be put into
a form that allows us to explicitly
enumerate time and then in chapter 4
and then again we'll see in chapter
seven and eight
we have two ways to deal with time
broadly discrete time continuous time
discrete time
actually models
discrete
slices of time
sequentially
and generates parameterizations for like
hidden States and observations at
different explicit time points
in contrast
The Continuous time generative model
which is being shown like with these one
twos and threes instead of the D B and A
they're being shown juxtaposed in figure
four three to emphasize their structural
similarities
however
whereas the discrete time model is
explicitly predicting States and
observations at different time points
The Continuous time model
it's B Matrix equivalent
is not the next state but rather the
derivative of the states
and so the continuous time model has
more in common with a Taylor expansion
or a Volterra expansion or generalized
coordinates of motion
so in either case
pomdps
help us
focus our statistical and informational
power
on constrained sets of models
that
are not too restrictive
if we're willing to abide by certain
uh standard
modeling
practices like that the past can't
influence the future except through the
presence
or that like a derivative can't have an
influence on its second derivative
without influencing the first derivative
first
so under those standard modeling
assumptions
that uh
reduce the state space vastly
like one can imagine if there was 10
time points or 10 derivatives and you
did all by all you'd end up with a lot
of edges
but if you constrain it to time points
can only influence next time points and
derivatives can only influence the next
derivatives then
your model scales linearly with time
points or derivatives rather than
um Supra linearly
so PMT pmtp is one implementation
architecture
that generates generative models which
are compatible with The Continuous Flow
Bayesian physics underlying
just like you might have some flow or
field equations for electromagnetics
and then you have some discrete time
realization
in your simulation
that is the relationship
I I have a question huh
so if you say it's like a Taylor series
then this is a somehow deterministic
isn't it I mean in the beginning in the
Taylor series you say what functions you
want to decompose and then all the parts
are a little bit deterministic
but but is it what we were trying to
model here
or am I completely wrong
I mean it is a series you already I mean
it's maybe infinite but
um
but you know from the beginning what the
what they want what the individual
components are
anyone else want to give a thought on
that or I can
add something
well
it can be deterministic
so you could have a model where for
example like
there isn't
[Music]
um
like there's an identity Matrix for a so
like hidden states are fully observable
or you could have one where the state
transitions are fully deterministic as
well in the discrete time case okay now
in the continuous case
um
is it deterministic well
from a given hidden state
you could have a deterministic or
non-deterministic emission of
observations
you can have probabilistic action
selection
that influences how States change
Through Time
and the way that they change their time
um could be sampled hence also not
deterministic
um
and I think
the
Taylor series
and variational inference have a lot in
common in that you do have to commit to
like a given family of distributions
that you're wanting to fit
but then within a given variational
family so you have some data set and you
say and now I'm going to fit this type
of distribution to it
you might fit that with the stochastic
gradient descent or there might be a
deterministic algorithm to fit it
but
it's a little bit too broad of a brush
to think about the bigger picture of
using these models and simply say that
they're deterministic or
non-deterministic
I hope that makes sense because it is a
very subtle
question yeah okay yeah thanks
like I'm wondering if you could have a
non-determined like can a function have
a uh stochastic derivative
well I don't know but I mean somehow if
we think of the environment that
produces new
input
um
and we don't know that environment
then somehow on an undeterministic
factor is there right
yes the generative process is not shown
here
the generative process external States
is handing observations in so the GM
to kind of bring back the question it
unrolls
and it shows
the agent's perspective
this is necessary and sufficient to
define the agents
but here's the great unknown that's
handing the observations to the agent
so the GM
can be seen as like the cognitive
architecture of the agents
it is not describing the total scenario
that the particular partition is showing
so that's one other difference X um this
s
is not the actual external States
this is the agent's variational estimate
of external States Ali
I think the remark on page 24 of pass
integrals paper
might help to understand this issue a
little bit better especially the second
paragraph which says that from the
perspective of an observer Behavior will
appear to be fulfilling the epistemic
and pragmatic imperatives afforded by
expected free energy so it's basically
uh the control versus planning or a
homeostasis versus allostasis when we
look at the inference from the point of
view of the internal states of the agent
and because only the from that
perspective can we talk about reducing
the generalized free energy right so
uh there's a fundamental difference
between looking at this agent from its
internal State's point of view and
looking at it from the external from the
point of view of an external Observer I
don't know if it makes sense but uh
although they're complementary to each
other but uh in a sense they're
fundamentally different
thank you and um
just to to look ahead to nine though I
wonder if this might
be uh useful to see in six
is and it relates to the map territory
so here's figure 4.3 is in the middle
we're parameterizing a PO mdp with real
computers
about a rat in a teammase or an ant in a
colony or a cyber physical entity so
we're parameterizing this pomdp
but that pomdp
is in a parameterized environment as
well
and six kind of brings us
to that
but it would be awesome to see more
connective tissue
between the particular partition
which is where the physics
is inheriting from flows on the
particular partition
and how that relates to this view from
the inside of a cognitive agent
um okay in the final
um
minutes of this chapter six
okay last week I think we explored a
little bit about how b and a are
um two different variables they're not
directly connected to each other but
they kind of work as a team like B
increments the hidden State along and
then the hidden State emits an
observation
um good regulator we talked a little bit
with Bronwyn at office hours we explored
um good regulator theorem and
cybernetics and requisite diversity
um
we talked about what what happens to bad
regulators
um we explored also in the office hours
last week a little bit of the discussion
around the blanket trick
and about how affordance is handled in
active and some similarities and
contrasts with how it is handled in
um
other areas of like other threads of
thinking in ecological psychology
um
in the coming
second discussion on chapter six
we can return to these bottom three
questions
temporal depth
cognitive systems outside the brain
and similarities and differences with
active inference and other modeling
any final remarks on this
all right awesome I will stop recording
let us take
um a two minute break and then we will
begin for cohort three thank you all